Ricardo Camacho Castilla

(+61) 0404 721 837
East Melbourne, Australia
rcamachocast@student.unimelb.edu.au

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

I am a civil and environmental engineer with a Master's degree in Civil Engineering for Risk Mitigation from Politecnico di Milano. Currently, I am a PhD Candidate at the University of Melbourne. My research focuses on the relationship between urban planning and disaster risk reduction, studying human settlements risk, sustainability, and dynamics before and after a disastrous event, through spatial analysis and remote sensing. I am a researcher at the Centre for Disaster Management and Public Safety (CDMPS), the Centre for Spatial Data Infrastructures and Land Administration (CSDILA), and the Research Group in EO and AI. I am proactive and methodic, have strong analytic and leadership skills, and have excellent team-working capabilities.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Tutor, The University of Melbourne, Parkville (AUS) – (Jul 2022 – Present)

 Assisted the lecturer on the subject: Digital Infrastructure Systems Capstone (previously Integrated Spatial Systems) (GEOM30012), tutoring students, demonstrating laboratory equipment, and grading assignments.

Instructor professor (Full-time Young Lecturer), University of Los Andes, Bogota (COL) - (Jan 2017 - Jan 2020)

- Leader of the Geomatics area in the Civil and Environmental Engineering Department
- As the Geomatics subject coordinator, I introduced UAVs and LiDAR technologies into the curriculum and created new fieldwork as a surveying/GIS integration.
- As an active member of the Statics subject team, I implemented a flipped classroom methodology with innovative resources to advocate students' autonomy in the learning process.
- I supervised six undergraduate and four graduate research theses. Four of these were published in international congresses.
- Co-convened, alongside NASA and Water Youth Network, the international event Hack the Risk Smart Solutions on Water Issues and Floods in April 2019.

Researcher, University of Los Andes, Bogota (COL) – (Jan 2017 – Dec 2020)

- Member of the research group on Urban and Regional Sustainability (SUR)
- Member of the Research Portfolio on Historical Ecology and Social Memory (EHMS)
- Member of the DRR Working Group of the United Nations Major Group for Children and Youth (UNMGCY).
- Member of the FIGs' Commission 7 on Cadastre and Land Management
- Five research articles were published in ISI Q1 journals, and one is currently in the press. Oral and poster publications in over ten conferences and congresses.

EDUCATION

PhD in Engineering & IT

The University of Melbourne, Parkville (AUS) – (Dec 2020 – Present)

Thesis: "Spatial dynamics of the informal urban growth in disaster-prone cities: impact on resilience and sustainability practices." Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Jagannath Aryal | Prof. Abbas Rajabifard

MSc in Civil Engineering for Risk Mitigation

Politecnico di Milano, Lecco (ITA) – (Sep 2014 – Dec 2016)

Thesis: "Enhancing structured and organized post-disaster damage loss data according to the SFDRR. Case: June 2013 flooding in Vall d'Aran and the Pyrenees" Advisor: Prof. Scira Menoni | Dr Ouejdane Mejri

Bachelor in Environmental Engineering

University of Los Andes, Bogota (COL) – (Aug 2010 – Oct 2014)

Bachelor in Civil Engineering

University of Los Andes, Bogota (COL) - (Jan 2010 - Mar 2014)

EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

Woodworking, gardening, sailing.

SKILLS

- Languages:
- Computer skills:

Spanish: Native speaker – English: Full proficiency – Italian: A2 level MS Office, ArcGIS, QGIS, AutoCAD, Revit, Pix4D, Python, R